<manual>
<chapter id="chapter-manual-structure">
<title>Manual Structure</title>

<section>
<p>An <cite>XMLMan</cite> manual has a hierarchical structure, consisting of a collection of chapters which each contain sections (and optionally nested sub-sections) that ultimately contain the actual content.</p>
</section>

<section id="section-manual-structure-manual">
<title>The Manual</title>

<p>The top level of an <cite>XMLMan</cite> document are the <code>&lt;manual&gt;</code> tags, which enclose the complete manual.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A manual can contain a number of tags, as follows.</p>

<section>
<title>Title</title>

<p>The manual title is contained in <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tags. This is the title used for the whole manual, and will be output somewhere near to the top of the page as determined by the individual output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;The XMLMan Manual&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A title is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Strapline</title>

<p>The manual strapline is contained in <code>&lt;strapline&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be a short description of the manual or its subject, which is included near the manual title in a manner determined by the individual output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;strapline&gt;Generate RISC&amp;nbsp;OS documentation from XML&lt;/strapline&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A strapline is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Credit</title>

<p>The manual credit is contained in <code>&lt;credit&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be a credit for the authorship of the manual or its subject, which is included near the manual title in a manner determined by the individual output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;credit&gt;&amp;copy; Stephen Fryatt, 2018-2025&lt;/credit&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A credit is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Date</title>

<p>The manual date is contained in <code>&lt;date&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be the date of the manual or its subject, which is included near the manual title in a manner determined by the individual output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;date&gt;27 March 2025&lt;/date&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A date is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup &ndash; as text, the formatting of the date is left up to the manual author.</p>

<p>The date is commonly used with an <ref id="external-definition">external definition</ref>, allowing the date to be generated by the build system which is calling <cite>XMLMan</cite> &ndash; for example <code>&lt;date&gt;&lt;define name=&quot;builddate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/date&gt;</code> would insert the text which was assigned to the <name>builddate</name> definition at the command line.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Version</title>

<p>The manual version is contained in <code>&lt;version&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be the version number of the manual or its subject, which is included near the manual title in a manner determined by the individual output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.00&lt;/version&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A version is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup &ndash; as text, the formatting, structure and meaning is left up to the manual author.</p>

<p>The version is commonly used with an <ref id="external-definition">external definition</ref>, allowing the information to be generated by the build system which is calling <cite>XMLMan</cite> &ndash; for example <code>&lt;version&gt;&lt;define name=&quot;buildversion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/version&gt;</code> would insert the text which was assigned to the <name>buildversion</name> definition at the command line.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>

<p>The manual summary is contained in <code>&lt;summary&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be a brief description of the manual, which could be used alongside its title in an external index of manuals. It is not currently used by any of the output modes.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The &lt;cite&gt;XMLMan&lt;/cite&gt; manual documents the
  use of the software, covering the format of the source files and the
  creation of the resulting manual documents.&lt;/summary&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A summary is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Resources</title>

<p>The manual resources provide the top-level node of the <ref id="chapter-resources">hierarchical resources structure</ref>, which are described in more detail in <ref id="chapter-resources"/>.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;resources&gt;
    &lt;images&gt;images/main&lt;/images&gt;
  &lt;/resources&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>
</section>

<section>
<title>Chapters and Indexes</title>

<p>The manual can contain <ref id="section-manual-structure-chapters">chapters and indexes</ref>, which are normally used to hold the content.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;index&gt;
     &lt;!-- The index contents --&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;

  &lt;chapter&gt;
     &lt;!-- The first chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;

  &lt;chapter&gt;
     &lt;!-- The second chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;
&lt;/manual&gt;</code>
</section>

<section>
<title>Sections</title>

<p>In addition to chapters and indexes, the manual can also contain stand-alone <ref id="section-manual-structure-sections">sections</ref> holding content.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
     &lt;!-- The section contents --&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/manual&gt;</code>
</section>
</section>


<section id="section-manual-structure-chapters">
<title>Chapters and Indexes</title>

<p>The main structure of a manual consists of chapters, indexes and sections, nested hierarchically. There are different ways of doing this, allowing a number of different configurations to be created.</p>

<p>Chapters &ndash; and their close relation indexes &ndash; exist at the top level of the manual, breaking it up into logical blocks.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;index&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Contents&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;chapterlist/&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;

  &lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;!-- The first chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;

  &lt;chapter id=&quot;second-chapter&quot;&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Chapter 2&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;!-- The second chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;
&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>The main difference between indexes and chapters is that chapters receive a number, whereas indexes don&rsquo;t. Indexes are usually reserved for tables of contents or indexes, so that these don&rsquo;t affect the numbering of the actual chapters within the document.</p>

<p>Both chapters and indexes can take an <name>id</name> attribute, which allows an <ref id="documents-references">internal reference</ref> to be associated with them.</p>

<section>
<title>External source files</title>

<p>In a large document, it may be desirable to break the source up into more than one file. This can be done at a chapter or index level, moving complete units out into their own sub files. To achive this, an alternative <intro>empty</intro> form of the <code>&lt;chapter&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;index&gt;</code> tags can be used to move their contents into external separate files.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;index file=&quot;index.xml&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;!-- The first chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;

  &lt;chapter file=&quot;chapter2.xml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>The empty chapter or index takes a <name>file</name> attribute, which supplies the name of the file containing the chapter definition described below. Empty tags do <em>not</em> take an <name>id</name> attribute, however: this should be in the definition that the empty tag points to.</p>

<p>The two ways to define chapters and indexes are interchangeable. In the example above, Chapter&nbsp;1 remains inline, whilst the index and Chapter&nbsp;2 have been defined in external files. This makes it possible to structure a manual in whatever way makes sense from a maintenance point of view.</p>

<p>These external chapter and index files are structured as manuals containing a single chapter or index. For example, the <file>chapter2.xml</file> would simply contain the chapter that would otherwise have been inline.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;chapter id=&quot;second-chapter&quot;&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Chapter 2&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;!-- The second chapter contents --&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;
&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>Note that it is not permissible to nest external references: the <code>&lt;chapter&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;index&gt;</code> tags in the external files must not be of the empty form.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Title</title>

<p>The chapter or index title is contained in <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tags. These will be output at the start of the chapter or index, in a format appropriate to each of the output modes. Chapters (but not indexes) will be numbered sequentially, and this number will be written in front of the title.</p>

<code>&lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;The Opening Chapter&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;!-- The chapter contents --&gt;

&lt;/chapter&gt;</code>

<p>A title is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>

<p>The chapter summary is contained in <code>&lt;summary&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be a brief description of the chapter, and will be used alongside the chapter title if an output mode needs to write the chapter into a separate file or section of the document.</p>

<code>&lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The opening chapter introduces some of the concepts used
  by &lt;cite&gt;XMLMan&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/summary&gt;

  &lt;!-- The chapter contents --&gt;

&lt;/chapter&gt;</code>

<p>A summary is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Resources</title>

<p>The chapter resources provide a node of the <ref id="chapter-resources">hierarchical resources structure</ref> which can override settings from the parent manual. These are described in more detail in <ref id="chapter-resources"/>.</p>

<code>&lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;resources&gt;
    &lt;images&gt;images/chapter2&lt;/images&gt;
  &lt;/resources&gt;

  &lt;!-- The chapter contents --&gt;

&lt;/chapter&gt;</code>
</section>

<section>
<title>Chapter list</title>

<p>The chapter list is a single empty tag which within an index or chapter allows a list of the chapters defined in the document to be output in the form of a table of contents for the document.</p>

<p>How this is done will depend on the output mode, but where the necessary IDs have been defined, it will generally involve clickable-links to the chapters themselves.</p>

<code>&lt;index&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Contents&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;chapterlist/&gt;
&lt;/index&gt;</code>

<p>Chapters will be included if they have a title defined; those without will be omitted.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Sections</title>

<p>The content of the chapter is held within <ref id="section-manual-structure-sections">sections</ref>.</p>

<code>&lt;chapter&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
     &lt;!-- The first section contents --&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
     &lt;!-- The second section contents --&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/chapter&gt;</code>

<p>There can be one or more setions within a chapter, which allows it to be split up into multiple blocks with their own sub-headings.</p>

</section>
</section>


<section id="section-manual-structure-sections">
<title>Sections</title>

<p>A section contains a block of content within a manual, which itself can include further nested sections.</p>

<p>Sections can take an <name>id</name> attribute, which allows an <ref id="documents-references">internal reference</ref> to be associated with them.</p>

<section>
<title>Title</title>

<p>The optional section title is contained in <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tags. These will be output at the start of the section, in a format appropriate to each of the output modes &ndash; usually in the form of sub-headings to the parent chapter, index or section. Sections will be numbered sequentially when contained within a numbered chapter, and this number will be written in front of the title.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;The First Section&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;!-- The section contents --&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;</code>

<p>A title is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>

<p>The section summary is contained in <code>&lt;summary&gt;</code> tags. This is intended to be a brief description of the section, and will be used alongside the section title if an output mode needs to write the section into a separate file.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The first section introduces some of the concepts used
  by &lt;cite&gt;XMLMan&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/summary&gt;

  &lt;!-- The section contents --&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;</code>

<p>A summary is a single <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block object</ref> containing text and markup.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Resources</title>

<p>The section resources provide a node of the <ref id="chapter-resources">hierarchical resources structure</ref> which can override settings from the parent section, chapter or index. These are described in more detail in <ref id="chapter-resources"/>.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;resources&gt;
    &lt;images&gt;images/chapter2&lt;/images&gt;
  &lt;/resources&gt;

  &lt;!-- The section contents --&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;</code>
</section>

<section>
<title>Chapter list</title>

<p>The chapter list is a single empty tag which within a section allows a list of the sections defined at the same level within the current parent to be output in the form of a table of contents. Used in an opening section of a chapter or section, this will produce a list of the sections within it.</p>

<p>How this is done will depend on the output mode, but where the necessary IDs have been defined, it will generally involve clickable-links to the chapters themselves.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Contents&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;chapterlist/&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</code>

<p>Sections will be included if they have a title defined; otherwise they will be omitted.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Sections</title>

<p>If needed, sections can be nested to produce sub-sections.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Section&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sub-SectionSection&lt;/title&gt;

     &lt;!-- The first sub-section contents --&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sub-Section&lt;/title&gt;

     &lt;!-- The second sub-section contents --&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</code>

<p>Where titles are used, these will be nested using dots or points: &lsquo;Chapter&nbsp;1&rsquo; would contain &lsquo;Section&nbsp;1.1&rsquo;, which in turn would contain &lsquo;Section&nbsp;1.1.1&rsquo;, and so on. In theory there is no limit to the depth at which sections can be nested, but individual output modes may impose their own limits (for example, HTML has only got the heading tags <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> to <code>&lt;h6&gt;</code> to use for headings, so this will impose a limit for the depth that is possible).</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contents</title>

<p>Alongside the objects described above, the content of a section consists of zero or more <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block objects</ref> such as paragraphs, lists or blocks of code.</p>

<code>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Section&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This is the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;This is a quotation which follows it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</code>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
</manual>