<manual>
<title>XMLMan</title>

<strapline>Generate RISC&nbsp;OS documentation from XML</strapline>
<credit>&copy; Stephen Fryatt, 2018-2024</credit>
<version>Version <define name="version" /></version>
<date><define name="date" /></date>

<index>
<title>Contents</title>

<chapterlist/>
</index>


<chapter>
<title>Licence</title>

<section>
<p><cite>XMLMan</cite> is licensed under the EUPL, Version&nbsp;1.2 only (the &ldquo;Licence&rdquo;); you may not use this work except in compliance with the Licence.</p>

<p>You may obtain a copy of the Licence at <link href="http://joinup.ec.europa.eu/software/page/eupl" flatten="true">http://joinup.ec.europa.eu/software/page/eupl</link>.</p>

<p>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the Licence is distributed on an &ldquo;<strong>as is</strong>&rdquo; basis, <strong>without warranties or conditions of any kind</strong>, either express or implied.</p>

<p>See the Licence for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the Licence.</p>

<p>The source for <cite>XMLMan</cite> can be found alongside this binary download, at <link href="https://github.com/steve-fryatt/XMLMan" flatten="true">https://github.com/steve-fryatt/XMLMan</link>.</p>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

<section>
<p><cite>XMLMan</cite> is a tool for generating documentation in a variety of formats from an XML source. It is written in C, and can be compiled to run on platforms other than RISC&nbsp;OS.</p>
</section>
</chapter>



<chapter>
<title>Documents</title>

<section>
<p>An <cite>XMLMan</cite> document consists of one or more XML files. They are notionally in UTF-8 encoding, although users creating files on RISC&nbsp;OS can avoid this by sticking to ASCII and using entities for the &ldquo;top-bit&rdquo; characters. This approach also makes it easier to store the files in source code management systems on other platforms.</p>

<p>The files mostly follow the standard XML syntax rules, which are as follows.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Tags are enclosed in &lt; and &gt; angle brackets, and use lower case.</p></li>
<li><p>Attribute names are in lower case, and their values are strings enclosed in double-quotes.</p></li>
<li><p>Entities are lower case text enclosed by &amp; and a semicolon. A subset of the HTML&nbsp;5 entities are supported.</p></li>
<li><p>The &lt;, &gt;, &quot; and &amp; characters are reserved, and must <em>always</em> be represented by the <code>&amp;lt;</code>, <code>&amp;gt;</code>, <code>&amp;quot;</code> and <code>&amp;amp;</code> entities when they appear in the manual text.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Comments are enclosed in <code>&lt;!--</code> and <code>--&gt;</code>, and can span multiple lines.</p>

<p>There is one small extension to the XML syntax, which is that some attributes can contain their own entities <em>and</em> tags. These are used sparingly, and will be clearly documented when they arise.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Character sets and encodings</title>

<p><cite>XMLMan</cite> source files are always treated as being in UTF-8. To make it easier to work on different platforms, many standard HTML&nbsp;5 entities are supported &ndash; for example <code>&amp;ndash;</code> for the en-dash in this sentence, or <code>&amp;Aacute;</code> for a capital A with an acute accent (&Aacute;). By sticking to standard &ldquo;ASCII-range&rdquo; characters and using entities, it is possible to create files which can be safely edited on both RISC&nbsp;OS and other platforms.</p>

<p>The encoding used for output files is specified when calling <cite>XMLMan</cite> from the command line. Characters which can be represented in the target encoding will be converted and written to the output, while those which can&rsquo;t will be replaced by a question mark &ndash; a warning will be issued for each one. Some output modes handle the conversion differently, and this is documented in their specific sections of this manual.</p>

<p>The encodings listed in <ref id="table-encodings" /> are supported.</p>

<table id="table-encodings" title="Supported output encoding types">
<columns>
<coldef>Encoding</coldef>
<coldef>Parameter</coldef>
</columns>
<row><col>Acorn Latin 1</col><col>AcornL1</col></row>
<row><col>Acorn Latin 2</col><col>AcornL2</col></row>
<row><col>Unicode UTF-8</col><col>UTF8</col></row>
<row><col>7 Bit</col><col>7Bit</col></row>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Internal references</title>

<p>Internal references link from areas of the text to objects such as chapters, sections, tables and code blocks (&ldquo;listings&rdquo;). These enable items such as &ldquo;see Chapter 2&rdquo; or &ldquo;as shown in Table 4&rdquo; to be entered easily, along with hyperlinks where the output format allows for these.</p>

<p>Reference IDs are specified using the <name>id</name> attribute within appropriate target tags, and can be any alphanumeric text. However, references map to object IDs in HTML output and since the IDs <name>head</name>, <name>head-liner</name>, <name>body</name>, <name>body-liner</name>, <name>foot</name> and <name>foot-liner</name> are used within the page structure, these are not available within a manual.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>External definitions</title>

<p>It is possible to supply externally-sourced content for a manual, in the form of short text definitions supplied with the <param>-define</param> parameter on the command line. The primary use case for this functionality is to support the embedding of build dates and version numbers into software manuals.</p>

<p>In the manual document, these defines can be accessed using <code>&lt;define&gt;</code> tags.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;The software was built on &lt;define name=&quot;builddate&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

</section>

<section>
<title>The Manual</title>

<p>The top level of an <cite>XMLMan</cite> document are the <code>&lt;manual&gt;</code> tags, which enclose the complete manual.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A manual can contain a number of tags, as follows.</p>

<section>
<title>Title</title>

<p>The manual title is contained in <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tags. This is the title used for the whole manual.</p>

<code>&lt;manual&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;The XMLMan Manual&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;!-- The manual contents --&gt;

&lt;/manual&gt;</code>

<p>A title is a single paragraph-like object containing text and markup.</p>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter file="html-output.xml" />

<chapter>
<title>Version History</title>

<section>
<p>Here is a list of the versions of <cite>XMLMan</cite>, along with all of the changes made.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Test Build</title>

<p>Initial release for testing and feedback.</p>
</section>
</chapter>


<section>
<title>Updates and Contacting Me</title>

<p>If you have any comments about <cite>XMLMan</cite>, or would like to report any bugs that you find, you can email me at the address below.</p>

<p>Updates to <cite>XMLMan</cite> and more software for RISC&nbsp;OS computers can be found on my website at <link href="http://www.stevefryatt.org.uk/risc-os"/>.</p>

<p>Stephen Fryatt<br/>
email: <link href="mailto:info@stevefryatt.org.uk" flatten="true">info@stevefryatt.org.uk</link></p>
</section>
</manual>