<manual>
<chapter id="chapter-span-objects">
<title>Span Objects</title>

<section>
<p>A span object is an object which is contained within a &lsquo;paragraph level&rsquo; (or <ref id="chapter-block-objects">block</ref>) object. It forms the markup of much of the text within the document.</p>

<p>In general, span objects can be nested within each other as required to create the reqired semantic meaning. Where this isn&rsquo;t possible, it is stated in the descriptions below.</p>

<p>It is not possible to nest other types of object within span objects.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Simple semantic objects</title>

<p>The simple semantic objects apply a meaning to the text within them, which will usually be mapped to a display format by the individual output modes. A full list is given in <ref id="table-span-objects-simple"/>.</p>

<table title="Simple semantic objects" id="table-span-objects-simple">
<columns>
<coldef width="26">Object</coldef>
<coldef>Purpose</coldef>
</columns>
<row><col><code>&lt;cite&gt;...&lt;/cite&gt;</code></col><col>Citations</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;code&gt;...&lt;/code&gt;</code></col><col>In-line chinks of code</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;command&gt;...&lt;/command&gt;</code></col><col>Commands, such as *Commands</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;const&gt;...&lt;/const&gt;</code></col><col>Constant values </col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;em&gt;...&lt;/em&gt;</code></col><col>Lightly emphasised text</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;entry&gt;...&lt;/entry&gt;</code></col><col>Text to be entered by the user</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;event&gt;...&lt;/event&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a Wimp or Toolbox event</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;file&gt;...&lt;/file&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a file</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;function&gt;...&lt;/function&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a function or procedure</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;icon&gt;...&lt;/icon&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a button or icon in a window</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;intro&gt;...&lt;/intro&gt;</code></col><col>The introductorary reference to a word or concept</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;keyword&gt;...&lt;/keyword&gt;</code></col><col>A programming keyword</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;maths&gt;...&lt;/maths&gt;</code></col><col>A mathematical formula</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;message&gt;...&lt;/message&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a Wimp message</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;mouse&gt;...&lt;/mouse&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a mouse key</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;</code></col><col>A general name which isn&rsquo;t covered by another object</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;strong&gt;...&lt;/strong&gt;</code></col><col>Strongly emphasised text</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;swi&gt;...&lt;/swi&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a SWI call</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;type&gt;...&lt;/type&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a variable type</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;variable&gt;...&lt;/variable&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a variable</col></row>
<row><col><code>&lt;window&gt;...&lt;/window&gt;</code></col><col>The name of a window</col></row>
</table>

<p>Semantic objects can be nested, and may contain any of the other span objects documented in this section within their span.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Keypresses</title>

<p>Keypresses allow key combinations to be documented, and consist of a list of key objects contained within an outer keypress object.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;keypress&gt;&lt;key&gt;Return&lt;/key&gt;&lt;/keypress&gt;
or use &lt;keypress&gt;&lt;key&gt;Ctrl&lt;/key&gt;&lt;key&gt;M&lt;/key&gt;&lt;/keypress&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>This structure allows output modes to join the key combinations as they see fit, and also format the keys as they see fit (for example rendering each key as its own key-cap, if that is appropriate). For example, the line above might appear in some modes as &ldquo;Press Return or use Ctrl-M&rdquo;; in this output mode, it appears as &ldquo;Press <keypress><key>Return</key></keypress> or use <keypress><key>Ctrl</key><key>M</key></keypress>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The key objects can only contain plain text and entities: no other objects may be nested within them.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Menu entries</title>

<p>Menu entries allow selections from Wimp menus (or, indeed, any other sort of hierarchical menu structure) to be documented, and consist of a list of menu item objects contained within an outer menu object.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;Select &lt;menu&gt;&lt;item&gt;File&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Close&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/menu&gt; from the
main menu, then choose &lt;menu&gt;&lt;item&gt;Quit&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/menu&gt; from the iconbar
menu.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>This structure allows output modes to link the individual items in any way that they see fit. For example, the line above might be output as &ldquo;Select 'File &gt; Close' from the main menu, then choose 'Quit' from the iconbar menu&rdquo;; in this output mode, it appears as &ldquo;Select <menu><item>File</item><item>Close</item></menu> from the
main menu, then choose <menu><item>Quit</item></menu> from the iconbar menu.&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The item objects can only contain plain text and entities: no other objects may be nested within them.</p>
</section>


<section>
<title>Internal references</title>

<p>Internal references allow links to be created within a document to any other object which has an <name>id</name> attribute. The ID is given using an <name>id</name> attribute within the reference tag.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;For more details on &lt;ref id=&quot;paragraphs&quot;&gt;paragraphs of text&lt;/ref&gt;,
see &lt;ref id=&quot;paragraphs&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>Two forms of reference exist: <intro>span</intro> and <intro>empty</intro> references. Exactly how the two forms are used will depend on the requirements of the individual output mode, but in general:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>If text is available from a span reference, this will be used as the clickable-hyperlink or at least displayed in place in the document, whereas</p></li>

<li><p>If the reference is empty, the number and title of the target object will be used instead.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>The above example might therefore be presented along the following lines.</p>

<code>For more details on paragraphs of text, see Section 3.4. Paragraphs.</code>

<p>In the case of references to <ref id="section-block-objects-footnotes">footnotes</ref>, the reference will be inserted in what is considered to be the standard footnote style for the target output format.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>External links</title>

<p>External links allow references to resources outside the document, to anything with a valid URI. The required URI is supplied using the <name>href</name> attribute within the link tag.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;link href=&quot;https://www.example.com&quot;&gt;example website&lt;/link&gt;,
can be found at &lt;link href=&quot;https://www.example.com&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>Two forms of external link exist: <intro>span</intro> and <intro>empty</intro> links. Exactly how the two forms are used will depend on the requirements of the individual output mode, but in general:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>If text is available from a span link, this will be used as the clickable-hyperlink or at least displayed in place in the document, whereas</p></li>

<li><p>If the link is empty, the target URI will be used directly instead.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>The above example might therefore be presented along the following lines.</p>

<code>The example website can be found at https://www.example.com.</code>

<p>The optional <name>external</name> attribute can take the values <const>true</const> or <const>false</const>, with false being the default if the attribute is omitted. If true, output modes have the option to show the link as being &lsquo;external&rsquo; if they have a way of doing so.</p>

<p>Some output modes, particularly those which don&rsquo;t have a way to generate hyperlinks, can use an option to &rsquo;flatten&rsquo; the link. This can be controlled using the optional <name>flatten</name> attribute, which can take the values <const>true</const> or <const>false</const> and defaults to false if omitted. If true, a mode may choose to output the link text but omit the link itself. For example,</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;Email &lt;link href=&quot;mailto:email@example.com&quot; flatten=&quot;true&quot;&gt;email@example.com&lt;/link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>might generate the text</p>

<code>Email info@example.com.</code>

<p>with the value of the <name>href</name> attribute discarded when in a mode with no hyperlinks available.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>External definitions</title>

<p>The define object allows <ref id="documents-external-definitions">external definitions</ref> to be included within a document.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;This manual was created on &lt;define name=&quot;date&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>The <name>name</name> attribute identifies the definition to use, and the object will then be replaced by whatever value was passed to the <param>-define</param> parameter with the same name when <cite>XMLMan</cite> was called. For example, if the call was made with <entry>-define "date=2nd January 2025"</entry>, then the output would be</p>

<code>This manual was created on 2nd January 2025.</code>
</section>

<section>
<title>Line breaks</title>

<p>Line breaks allow a new line to be forced within a section of text.</p>

<code>&lt;p&gt;This is some text.&lt;br/&gt;
And this will always be on the next line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a new paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;</code>

<p>This example will ensure that there is always a line break &ndash; without any paragraph spacing &ndash; after the first full stop.</p>

<code>This is some text.
And this will be on the next line.

This will be a new paragraph.</code>
</section>
</chapter>
</manual>